Guide to the A. H. Sasse Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
A. H. Sasse papers
1907-1954
1922-1943
WA MSS S-3469
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.88
(8 boxes)
Business correspondence, circular letters, printed promotional materials, stock certificates, deeds, leases, receipts, ledgers, and plat maps documenting A. H. Sasse's businesses and investments, circa 1907-1954.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Michael Vinson on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2018.
Arrangement
Arranged into three series: I. Correspondence and Business Records, circa 1907-1954. II. Ledgers, 1923-1935. III. Maps, undated.
Biographical / Historical
A. H. Sasse was a businessman and investor in Pueblo, Colorado, circa 1907-1954. He invested in the gold mining, oil, and gas industries, and started several companies, including Fruitol Manufacturing and Supply Company, Golden Queen Mines and Investment Company, Searchlight Investments, A.H. Sasse Company, and A.H. Sasse Investments Association, which he referred to as his "Wiggletail" project.
Scope and Contents
Business correspondence, circular letters, printed promotional materials, stock certificates, deeds, leases, receipts, ledgers, and plat maps documenting A. H. Sasse's businesses and investments, circa 1907-1954. 12 autograph ledgers detail Sasse's investments, expenditures, and profits, including lists of investors. Includes annual lists of Sasse's properties, assets, and holdings and 4 plat maps relating to Sasse's investments in oil and gas in Arkansas, New Mexico, Louisiana, and Colorado. Includes materials relating to Fruitol Manufacturing and Supply Company, Golden Queen Mines and Investment Company, A.H. Sasse Company, Searchlight Investments, A.H. Sasse Investments Association, Goldfield Consolidated Mines Company, Owenwood Oil Corporation, Progressive Gold Mining and Milling Company, Vitek Oil and Refining Company, Bucher Smackover Trust Company, Moco Oil Corporation, Cosby Oil and Gas Company, Milton Oil Company, Royalty Products Company, Empire Chief Mining Company, Republic Insurance Company, Vindicator Development Corporation, E.L. Smith Oil Company, Champion Winkler Oil Corporation, Income Oil and Royalty Company, Silver Leaf Metals Incorporated, United Empire Gold Mines Company, Butler Oil and Refining Company, and Mytus Gold Corporation.
Gold mines and mining -- Colorado; Investments -- United States; Mineral investment -- Colorado; Mines and mineral resources -- Colorado; Mining leases -- United States; Oil and gas leases -- United States; Oil industries -- United States; Petroleum -- Arkansas; Petroleum -- Colorado; Petroleum -- Louisiana; Petroleum -- New Mexico; Petroleum -- Texas; Petroleum industry and trade -- United States; Colorado -- Economic conditions; Pueblo (Colo.); Cadastral maps; Ledgers (account books); Stock certificates; A.H. Sasse Company; A.H. Sasse Investments Association; Bucher Smackover Trust Company; Butler Oil and Refining Company; Champion Winkler Oil Corporation; Cosby Oil and Gas Company; E.L. Smith Oil Company; Empire Chief Mining Company; Fruitol Manufacturing and Supply Company; Golden Queen Mines and Investment Company; Income Oil and Royalty Company; Milton Oil Company; Moco Oil Corporation; Mytus Gold Corporation (Denver, Colo.); Owenwood Oil Corporation; Progressive Gold Mining and Milling Company; Republic Insurance Company; Royalty Products Company; Searchlight Investments; Silver Leaf Metals Incorporated; United Empire Gold Mines Company; Vindicator Development Corporation; Vitek Oil and Refining Company; Goldfield Consolidated Mines Company
- Correspondence and Business Records, circa 1907-1954; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Business correspondence, circular letters, printed promotional materials, stock certificates, deeds, leases, and receipts documenting A. H. Sasse's businesses and investments, circa 1907-1954.
  - Correspondence and business records, 1907-1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1936-1938 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1942-1943 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence and business records, 1944-1954 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence and business records, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Ledgers, 1923-1935; Series II; 1.05; (3 boxes)
  12 autograph ledgers detailing Sasse's investments, expenditures, and profits, including lists of investors.
  - Cash book, 1923-1930 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Expenses, 1923-1931 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Cash received, 1923-1929 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Paid by Wiggletail, 1923-1930 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Paid to Wiggletail, 1923-1928 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Daybook, 1923-1934 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Certificates, 1923-1925 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Cash payments, 1923-1926 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Interests, 1925-1931 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Account book, 1925-1926 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Account book, 1927-1929 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Account book, 1929-1935 (Box 7, Folder 48)
- Maps, undated; Series III; 2.17; (1 box)
  4 plat maps relating to Sasse's investments in oil and gas in Arkansas, New Mexico, Louisiana, and Colorado.
  - Owned and contracted properties of Virgil Helm and Associates, Shongaloo-Webster Parish, Louisiana Oil and Gas Field, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 49)
  - Oil and gas map of state of New Mexico, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 50)
  - Section of oil map showing Arkansas geology, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 51)
  - Oil map of Colorado, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 52)